I have been an organic farmer in Maine since the 1970s.
And no one can tell me or the other farmers here today
that we can't grow food without all of these toxic chemicals.
Over 140,000 family farms will close this year and nobody is talking about it.
140,000, guys.
Why is this happening?
Well, in the 1990s, Monsanto, later acquired by Bayer,
introduced something called Roundup Ready Crops,
which are crops that are genetically engineered to resist glyphosate,
which is the key ingredient in their weed killer, Roundup.
This then led to a massive explosion in the use of glyphosate in factory farming,
with now about 60% of total crops being treated with this pesticide.
The only problem is that Roundup causes cancer,
and Bayer has already had to pay tens of billions of dollars to settle these cases,
which obviously is not ideal for corporate profits.
In fact, Bayer is pushing a case in the Supreme Court right now
that blocks people from suing them if they get cancer from Roundup.
And the Trump administration is backing Bayer's bid to curb these Roundup lawsuits.
And for the farmers who say,
no, no, we don't want to chemicalize our food supply,
Bayer has methodically driven them one by one out of business,
with the help of President Barack Obama.
What has gotten us to this point is the mergers and consolidations of ag input suppliers.
In 2015, Monsanto and Bayer merged.
They were competing against each other, and that was during Obama's administration.
They didn't do a thing about that.
They let it happen.
When I started farming, we had five or six Arkansas-based seed companies.
Monsanto, there's none.
There's none.
They're all owned by Bayer.
Point blank, they created a monopoly to poison you,
and both parties are in on it.
Right now, there's a farm bill, H.R. 7567,
that Congress is expected to vote on this week
that codifies immunity for Bayer
and basically destroy organic farming going forward.
We cannot allow this to pass.